Finding Aid for A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture + Urban Planning Records 1876-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Minutes of Meetings 1929-2003
  - College of Architecture and Urban Planning
    - Architecture Program Faculty 1983-1986
      Minutes from the Architecture Program Faculty meetings document teaching assignments, upcoming lectures and exhibits, and the work of the Education Program Committee. The latter was an outcome of special curriculum meetings held by the Architecture Program Faculty Committee in May 1984. Minutes from the monthly/bi-monthly College Faculty Senate meetings include discussion of awards, budgets, promotions, scholarships, committee reports, lab fees and general announcements.
      - 1983-1986 (Box 20)
      - 1976-1983 (Box 29)
        [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022 ]
      - 1984-1986 (Box 29)
      - 1987-1991, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - 1992-1997 (Box 29)
    - College Faculty (Senate)
      - 1974-1977 (Box 20)
      - 1977-1980 (Box 20)
      - 1980-1983 (Box 20)
      - 1983-1986 (Box 20)
      - 1990-1995 (Box 50)
    - Executive Committee
      The members of the Executive Committee, which meet on a weekly/bi-weekly basis, represent the college faculty in policy-making decisions. Within the minutes of this committee, there is information pertaining to teaching appointments, affirmative action, and budgetary expenses.
      - List/Index 1973-1981 (Box 20)
      - 1973-1978, 4 folders (Box 20)
      - 1978-1986, 9 folders (Box 21)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 26)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 26)
      - 1970-1973 (Box 26)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 26)
      - 1974-1976 (Box 27)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 27)
      - 1979-1982 (Box 27)
      - 1983-1987 (Box 27)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 27)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 27)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 27)
      - 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 50)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 28)
      - 1995-1997 (very scattered) (Box 28)
      - 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 63)
        [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2030 ]
      - 1994-1995 (Box 63)
      - 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 63)
      - 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 63)
      - 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 63)
      - 1998-1999, 2 folders (Box 63)
      - 1999-2000, 3 folders (Box 64)
      - 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 64)
      - 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 64)
      - 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box 64)
    - Operations Committee
      The eight members of the Operations Committee are responsible for assisting the dean in the coordination and administrative functions of the college. The minutes from their meetings include discussion of teaching assignments, communications, and current budget accounts.
      - 1976-1977 (Box 21)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 21)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 21)
      - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 21)
        (chronological index in first folder)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 21)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 21)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 21)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 21)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 21)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 21)
    - Urban Planning Faculty 1975-1985
      The files on the monthly Urban Planning Faculty meetings include reports from various committees that deal with the Urban Planning portion of the college. The years 1981-1983 are missing from this group of minutes.
      - 1975-1985 (Box 21)
      - 1989-1998 (Box 50)
    - Administrative Committee
      - 1988-1989 (Box 26)
      - 1989-1991 (Box 26)
      - 1989-1998 (Box 50)
    - Faculty, CAUP
      - 1968-1974, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - 1974-1991 (Box 28)
    - Faculty Senate, CAUP
      - 1974-1980 (Box 28)
      - 1981-1988 (Box 28)
      - 1987-1990 (Box 28)
    - Alumni Society Board of Governors 1983-2001 (Box 50)
      - 1983-1997, 2 folders (Box 63)
      - 1997-2001, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - Cabinet Meetings 1988-1993
      - 1988-1989 (Box 26)
      - 1989-1993 (Box 50)
    - Joint Executive and Administrative Committees April 2, 1987 (Box 50)
- Dean's Administrative Files 1957-2008
  The Dean's Administrative Files series consists largely of subject files maintained by the dean's office and include documentation relating to the administration of the college as well as professional and sometimes personal activities of the deans. The series is organized in subseries corresponding to the tenure of individual deans, although a subseries may include material dating from a previous dean's tenure.
  - Wells Ira Bennett
    Dean Wells Ira Bennett's file consists of report issued by the Survey Committee of the College of Architecture and Design in 1948.
    - Report of the Survey Committee of the College of Architecture and Design 1948 (Box 2)
  - Reginald F. Malcolmson
    Dean Reginald F. Malcolmson's files were received in several accessions and consist of two overlapping alphabetical subject files.
    - 1956-1974
      Administrative Files, 1956-1974, of Dean Reginald Malcolmson are arranged alphabetically and include correspondence, memos, reports, position papers, and notes. The files date between 1956 and 1974 and include a few materials from the previous dean, Philip Youtz. However, the bulk of the files date between 1964 and 1974. Malcolmson's deanship (1964-1974) coincided with the period in which the college was preparing for a move to new facilities on the North Campus. The files document Malcolmson's administrative concerns with the move as well as his personal interest in the planning process. The files also contain material concerning the reorganization of the college and the relationship between the Art and Architecture departments. The series also includes a fair amount of material relating to Malcolmson's personal scholarly and professional activities; for example, materials concerning Malcolmson's Fulbright lectures in South America, and his ongoing relationship with various South American architects. In addition to the administrative files of the various deans contained in this collection the researcher should be aware that the Bentley Library also holds the personal collections of Director Emil Lorch and Deans Bennett and Youtz.
      - A (General) 1967-1970 (Box 2)
      - Action file 1964-1966 (Box 2)
      - Alpha Rho Chi 1957-1972 (Box 2)
      - American Institute of Architects (Detroit Chapter) 1967-1973 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Art Association 1956 (Box 2)
      - Appointment to Deanship 1964 (Box 2)
      - B (General) (Box 2)
      - Biographical (Box 2)
      - Birkerts, Gunnar, and Associates (Box 2)
      - Building Committee (Box 3)
        - 1966 (Box 3)
        - Report to the Faculty, 1965-1974 (Box 3)
      - C (General) 1969-1973 (Box 3)
      - Chronological File 1970-1974, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Chronological File (Dean's Personal) 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Collins, George R. 1960-1973 (Box 3)
      - Committee on International Exchange of Persons 1972-1973 (Box 3)
      - Committee on Regional Planning 1965 (Box 3)
      - Coppola, Horacio 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - Department of Architecture 1960-1971 (Box 3)
      - Dow, Alden B. 1959-1964 (Box 3)
      - Entenza, John D. 1964-1971 (Box 3)
      - Financial 1974 (Box 3)
      - Flores, Carlos 1968-1974 (Box 3)
      - Friedman, Yona 1967-1973 (Box 3)
      - Fulbright Lectures, South America 1969 (Box 3)
      - Future Worlds (lecture series) 1973 (Box 3)
      - G (General) 1970-1973 (Box 3)
      - Graduate Students, North Campus Study 1965-1966 (Box 3)
      - Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts 1965-1972 (Box 3)
      - Hejduk, John 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - International Conference on Space Structures 1964-1967 (Box 3)
      - K (General) 1970 (Box 3)
      - M (General) 1968-1974 (Box 3)
      - Memoranda (College Organization) 1964 (Box 3)
      - Metropolitan Fund (New Town) 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Society of Architects 1968 (Box 3)
      - N (General) 1974 (Box 3)
      - O (General) 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - P (General) 1968-1971 (Box 3)
      - Papers and Projects 1965-1973 (Box 3)
      - Pewabic Pottery 1961-1962 (Box 3)
      - Progressive Architecture, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Recommendations for Promotion 1967 (Box 3)
      - Roehm, J.M. (Reynolds Metals) 1970-1973 (Box 4)
      - Sketchbook, Malcolmson June 18, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Smith, Allan F. 1966-1967 (Box 4)
      - South American Correspondence 1969-1972 (Box 4)
      - Teaching 1974 (Box 4)
      - Television Program ("Architecture of the City") 1966 (Box 4)
      - W (General) 1970-1973 (Box 4)
      - Walter Gropius Exhibition 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - Williams, Amancio 1969-1972 (Box 4)
      - Youtz-High Rise Apartments, Ann Arbor 1959-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1959-1974
      The 1959-1974 Administrative Files of Dean Malcolmson (1.5 linear feet) are especially rich regarding the planning, construction, and move to the North Campus facilities. In addition, the personal files of Professors Edward Olencki and Walter Sanders supplement earlier accession materials relating to the college during the 1950s and early 1960s.
      - Accreditation of the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design (Box 6)
      - Buildings on Campus 1840-1960 (basic information) (Box 6)
      - Committees
        - Ad Hoc Building Program Committee 1967-1968 (Box 6)
        - Campus Planning Advisory Committee 1961-1962 (Box 6)
        - College Building Committee 1960-1970 (Box 6)
        - College Committee on Education 1957-1974 (Box 6)
        - College Committee on Rules and Regulations 1952-1972 (Box 6)
        - College Committee on Space and Planning 1965-1972 (Box 6)
        - Dean, College of Architecture and Design, Search Committee 1963-1964 (Box 6)
        - Educational Program Committee 1966-1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Exhibition Committee 1972-1976 (Box 6)
        - North Campus Planning Committee 1959-1964 (Box 6)
        - Student-Faculty Committee 1968-1974 (Box 6)
        - University Committee on Urban and Regional Planning 1966-1968 (Box 6)
      - North Campus Building: Design and Construction 1968-1974 (Box 7)
      - Professor's Personal Files
        - Edward Olencki 1949-1962 (Box 7)
        - Walter Sanders 1949-1969 (Box 7)
      - "Program Statement for New Facilities of the College of Architecture and Design," February 28, 1966 (Box 7)
      - Sesquicentennial Celebration 1967 (Box 7)
  - Robert C. Metcalf
    - 1970-1980
      The initial accession of Metcalf files consists of a long-range master plan for the college during the years 1970-1980, and a draft of a 1976 memorandum of understanding between the college and the Office of Academic Affairs.
      - Long-range Master Plan 1970-1980 (Box 4)
      - Office of Academic Affairs (draft of memorandum of understanding with) 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1964-1986
      The Administrative Files, 1964-1986 of Dean Metcalf (6.5 linear feet, received in the 1989-89 accession) cover a diverse range of topics. While the vast majority of the material dates from Metcalf's deanship, a few folders date from earlier periods when Metcalf was a faculty member or chairman of the Department of Architecture. In general, the administrative files relate to the internal organization of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning and to Dean Metcalf's participation in various professional organizations. Very little information exists here on Metcalf's private practice as an architect. The researcher should also note that post-1974 executive committee meeting minutes and faculty meeting minutes were not included in this accession.
      Perhaps the best overviews of the college during the Metcalf years can be gleaned from the "College of Architecture and Design Review Committee Report" (April 11, 1974), the so-called Norman Report, and from subsequent accreditation plans and reports. Since the reorganization of the college, the move to North Campus, and the search for a new dean were all happening simultaneously in 1974, file folder titles indicating one of these subjects may contain some information on all three events.
      For information on actual and proposed organizational changes in the college around 1974, the researcher should consult the Norman Report and "Environmental Programs - University of Michigan." Attempts to find a university-wide organizational scheme, which would consolidate environmental programs, led to new proposals after 1974 for a further restructuring of the college (see Administrative History). Although the College of Environmental Resources, Planning and Design never materialized it was seriously considered. As a consequence, thoughtful discussions on the overall direction of the architectural profession took place at that time and are documented in these files. The lengthy debates regarding reorganization of the college also led to a delay in the selection of a new dean which is documented in the "Dean, Search Committee" files. For those interested in interdisciplinary programs, which emerged especially after 1976, "Joint Ventures and Dual-Degree Programs" should be consulted.
      The researcher who is interested in architectural education during the Metcalf era should study those files found under the heading, "Students: Education and Related Activities." Although there is no useful summary of curriculum changes for the period, the Educational Program Committee (E.P.C.) files contain correspondence on the merits of new course offerings and note yearly changes in the education program. Information on student internships can be found in the Intern Programs files. Material on Project GROW and the North Central Property Owners Association can be found among the Projects and Community Service files. "Minority Enrollment" files (separate topical heading) document efforts of the college to attract and hold minority students. Correspondence regarding faculty informational visits to Detroit public schools, meetings with black alumni, and annual statistical reports are included here.
      The Annual Files under the heading "Research Activities" record the expanding volume and scope of research at the college during the 1974-1986 period. Architectural research projects predominate in these files, but scattered urban planning research projects are also included, especially during the 1980s. Perhaps the best general surveys of architectural research at the college can be obtained from the "Research Program Review, 1979" and from the reports, "Development Needs of the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory" (November 1982) and "Functional and Space Needs of the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory" (May 1983). While several projects undertaken by the Architecture and Planning Laboratory are documented under the heading "Research Activities," folders under "Energy Efficiency Programs" should also be consulted to study lab projects.
      Information on certification for architects can be found under "Michigan Board of Registration for Architects." Dean Metcalf was a prominent member of the Board of Registration and actively involved in examination procedures and licensing requirements. His views on these subjects can be found in his correspondence as a board member and as a member of the Sunset Legislation Committee. His remarks to the "Michigan Society of Architects Panel on Registration" in 1977 also address the issue of certification
      - Accreditation of the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Urban Planning
        - National Architectural Accrediting Board (Box 7)
        - Educational Development Plan 1976 (Box 7)
        - Survey 1978 (Box 7)
        - Visits and Reports 1976-1979 (Box 7)
        - North Central Accreditation Association (Box 7)
        - Evaluation and Planning Project (phase I, II) 1976-1979, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Accrediting and Jurying Visits of Robert C. Metcalf
        - Saudi Arabia 1983 (Box 7)
        - Southern University 1972 (Box 7)
        - Southern University 1984 (Box 7)
        - State University of New York at Buffalo 1985 (Box 7)
        - University of Utah 1977 (Box 7)
        - Virginia Polytechnic Institute 1982 (Box 7)
      - Admissions and Enrollment 1981-1986 (Box 7)
      - Chairman, Department of Architecture
        - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Search Committee 1964-1965 (Box 8)
      - College of Architecture and Design Review Committee
        - Minutes and Memoranda 1973-1974 (Box 8)
        - Report April 11, 1974 (Norman Report) (see also Box 46) (Box 8)
      - Commencements 1981-1986 (awards and speeches) (Box 8)
      - Continuing Education Programs 1975-1983, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Dean, College of Architecture and Urban Planning, Selection Process
        - Search Committee 1973-1974 (Box 8)
        - Search Committee 1975-1976 (Box 8)
      - Energy Efficiency Programs
        - Computer Based Building Cost Information System 1972-1974 (Box 8)
        - Energy Conservation, correspondence 1972-1980 (Box 8)
        - Energy Cost Avoidance Project, University of Michigan (ECAP)
          - General 1982-1986 (Box 8)
          - Pilot Study and Recommendations October, 1983 (Box 8)
          - Reports on Specific Buildings
            - Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library (Box 9)
            - Modern Languages Building (Box 9)
            - Physics and Astronomy Building (Box 9)
            - Power Center Building (Box 9)
            - School of Music Building (Box 9)
            - Space Research Building (Box 9)
        - Federal Office Building, Saginaw, Michigan 1975-1978 (solar energy systems) (Box 9)
        - Michigan Energy and Resource Research Association (MERRA) 1975-1977 (includes correspondence and proposals) (Box 9)
        - Mid-American Solar Energy Complex 1977-1979 (correspondence and newsletters) (Box 9)
        - Re-Design of the Art and Architecture Building (REAAB Project) 1977-1983 (re: energy cost reduction)
          - Preliminary Plans and Studies 1977-1978 (Box 9)
          - Progress and Final Reports 1979-1983 (Box 9)
      - Environmental Programs, University of Michigan
        - Center for Environmental Studies proposed 1960-1961 (Box 9)
        - College Committee on Environmental Studies 1969-1971 (Box 9)
        - College of Environmental Resources, Planning, and Design proposed 1974-1975 (Box 9)
        - Council for Environmental Planning 1975-1979, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Institute for Environmental Quality 1971 (Box 9)
        - School of Environmental Science and Design (proposed, 1970) (Box 9)
      - Job Placement Activities 1984-1985 (Box 9)
      - Joint Ventures and Dual-Degree Programs
        - College of Engineering 1975-1976 (Box 9)
        - Department of Psychology 1969 (adulthood and aging) (Box 9)
        - Master of Science Degree Program 1986 (Box 9)
        - Rome Program 1976 (Box 9)
        - School of Art 1977-1984 (interior design) (Box 9)
        - School of Business Administration 1976-1979 (Box 9)
        - School of Natural Resources
          - Integrative Studies Center 1978-1980 (Box 9)
          - Landscape Architecture 1981-1984 (Box 9)
          - Miscellaneous programs (Box 9)
        - School of Nursing 1977 (Box 9)
        - Vienna Program 1986 (Box 9)
      - Michigan Board of Registration for Architects
        - Correspondence 1975-1982 (Box 10)
        - Design Exam Workshops 1981-1984, 4 folders (Box 10)
        - Licensing Requirements and Legislation 1979-1983 (Box 10)
        - Sunset Legislation Committee 1976-1978 (correspondence, minutes and reports) (Box 10)
      - Michigan Society of Architects
        - Committee on Architects in Government, Education, and Industry 1979 (Box 10)
        - Continuing Education Consortium 1976-1979 (Box 10)
        - Panel on Registration 1977 (Box 10)
        - Region / Urban Design Assistance Teams, (includes "Huron Valley Inter-Urban Growth Analysis," June, 1978) (Box 10)
        - Task Force on Education 1981 (Box 10)
      - Minority Enrollment
        - Annual Reports and Statistics 1968-1986, 18 folders (Box 22)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2026 ]
        - Black Alumni (correspondence and meetings) (Box 10)
        - Martin Luther King Commemoration 1985 (Box 10)
      - National Policy Center on Housing and Living Arrangements for Older Americans (N.H.C.)
        - General 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 10)
          (includes correspondence, newsletters, reports, and surveys)
        - Annual Files 1971-1987, 15 folders (Box 10)
        - Architectural Design Research Symposium November, 1981 (Box 10)
        - Demise of N.H.C. 1983 (Box 10)
        - "Developmental Needs of the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory" November, 1982 (Box 10)
        - Fremont, Michigan, Elderly Housing Study 1981-1982 (Box 10)
        - "Housing for the Elderly in Midland, Michigan" 1982 (N.H.C. report) (Box 10)
      - Research Activities, College of Architecture and Urban Planning (Box 11)
        - "Functional and Space Needs of the Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory" May 1983 (Box 11)
        - Health Services Research 1983 (Box 11)
        - Monroe County Library 1977 (wind energy proposal) (Box 11)
        - Passive Solar Design Curriculum 1980 (proposed) (Box 11)
        - Replacement Hospital Project 1981-1983 (room mock-ups and evaluation) (Box 11)
        - Research Program Review 1979, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Workshop on Court House Design 1974 (Box 11)
      - School of Natural Resources, Review Committee 1969-1970 (Metcalf's notes) (Box 11)
      - Space Allocation: Problems and Solutions 1968-1986, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Students: Education and Related Activities
        - American Institute of Architects, Association of Student Chapters
          - Committee on Student Affairs 1969 (Box 12)
          - Correspondence 1981-1986 (Box 12)
          - National Forums
            - "Expanding Horizons in Architecture," 1984 (Box 12)
            - " Turmoil, Education, Evolution," 1968 (Box 12)
        - "Architecture: Education and the Profession," 1969 (conference at the University of Michigan) (Box 12)
        - Concentration Requirements 1976-1977 (Box 12)
        - Counseling 1969-1984 (Box 12)
        - Course Problems 1973-1984 (Box 12)
        - Design Curriculum 1977-1980 (forums on) (Box 12)
        - Educational Program Committee (E.P.C.) 1972-1986, 9 folders (Box 12)
        - Grading and Course Evaluation Policy 1971-1980 (Box 12)
        - Intern Programs
          - Intern Development Program (AIA) 1981-1986 (Box 12)
          - Preceptorship Program 1972-1974 (Box 12)
          - Progressive Exposure Program for the Progressive Education of Post Graduates (PEP II), 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Projects and Community Service
          - Brookview Project 1977-1980 (Fenton, Michigan youth home) (Box 13)
          - Climbing Tree 1975-1976 (alternative school) (Box 13)
          - Community Design Centers 1970 (Box 13)
          - Cooperative Area Manpower Planning System (CAMPS) 1969-1972 (Box 13)
          - Grass Roots Organization of Workers (Project GROW) (Detroit) 1969-1980 (Box 13)
          - North Central Property Owners Association (Ann Arbor) 1972-1976 (Box 13)
        - Professional Skills Alliance 1970-1971 (Box 13)
        - Requests for Student Projects 1976-1986 (Box 13)
        - Questionnaires 1972-1977 (Box 13)
        - Rethink Committee 1972 (re: curriculum changes) (Box 13)
        - Teaching Assignments 1960-1980 (Box 13)
      - Subcommittee on the Future Environment of the University 1973-1974 (Box 13)
        (includes surveys and correspondence)
      - Urban Planning Program 1979-1986 (Box 13)
        (includes reports and faculty meeting minutes)
      - Visual Information Materials Laboratory (VIM Lab) 1972-1974 (Box 13)
    - 1967-1988